Academic CV Last Updated: December 20, 2022

# JOSEPH BLOCHBERGER, PE

Professional Engineer & Graduate Student
Department of Civil & Systems Engineering
The Johns Hopkins University
Latrobe Hall
3400 N. Charles St.
Baltimore, MD 21218

E-mail: jblochb2@jhu.edu

Website: <a href="https://www.joeblochberger.com/">https://www.joeblochberger.com/</a>

#### PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Experienced multidisciplinary engineer well-versed engineering acoustics, analyzing sensor data, and sonar systems engineering. Committed to studying the performance of fielded and future engineering systems using real-world data, engineering principles, and applied probability / statistics. Licensed professional engineer in the Commonwealth of Virginia. Currently enrolled as a PhD student in Civil & Systems Engineering at The Johns Hopkins University (advised by Prof. Tak Igusa).

**Research Interests:** Creativity in Design, Data-Driven Analysis, Decision Analysis, Design of Complex Systems, Design Synthesis, Operations Research, Predictive Analytics, Probability & Stochastic Processes, Signal Processing, Simulation-Based Design Under Uncertainty, Systems Engineering, Systems Science

## **EDUCATION & LICENSURE**

**Professional Engineer, License No. 0402060705**, Virginia Department of Professional & Occupational Regulation

Master of Science, Mechanical Engineering, The Pennsylvania State University (Penn State)

**Bachelor of Science, Mechanical Engineering**, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University (Virginia Tech)

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

- Project Manager (concurrently Assistant Program Manager), The Johns Hopkins University Applied Physics Laboratory, 09/2020 to present
- PhD Student (Civil & Systems Engineering), The Johns Hopkins University, 08/2022 to present
- Test & Evaluation Engineer, The Johns Hopkins University Applied Physics Laboratory, 03/2019 to present
- Systems Engineer (Acoustics), General Dynamics Electric Boat, 05/2015 to 03/2019
- Research Assistant, **Energy Harvesting and Mechatronics Research Laboratory** (Advised by Prof. Lei Zuo), Virginia Tech, 01/2015 to 05/2015
- Engineering Intern, **General Dynamics Electric Boat**, 06/2014 to 01/2015
- R&D Engineering Intern, **Kollmorgen**, 01/2014 to 05/2014
- Lab Operator, Virginia Tech Math Emporium, Virginia Tech, 2013 to 2014

## **TECHNICAL PROFICIENCIES**

- Languages: MATLAB, MySQL, Mathematica, Octave, R, Python, CSS, HTML, Javascript
- *Skills:* Acoustics, Analyzing Sensor Data, Applied Probability / Statistics, Data-Driven Analysis, Independent Test & Evaluation, Mechanical Engineering, Noise Control, Professional Engineer, Project Management, Sonar, Signal Processing, Systems Engineering, Systems Science, Vibrations

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

# Peer-reviewed Conference Proceedings

**J. Blochberger**, "Analysis of Structural Acoustic Design Variables for a Periodically Stiffened Plate Using the Finite Element Method," *Proceedings of the ASME 2019 International Mechanical Engineering Congress & Exposition. Volume 11: Acoustics, Vibration, and Phononics.* Salt Lake City, Utah, USA. November 11-14, 2019. V011T01A007. ASME. https://doi.org/10.1115/IMECE2019-10259

## Master of Science in Mechanical Engineering Capstone

**J. Blochberger**, "Analysis of Structural Acoustic Design Variables for a Periodically Stiffened Plate Using the Finite Element Method," The Pennsylvania State University. Advisor: Prof. Alok Sinha. December, 2018.

# **NON-REFEREED TECHNICAL REPORTS**

- The Johns Hopkins University Applied Physics Laboratory
  - Lead author on multiple engineering analysis reports regarding real-world performance quantification of fielded sonar systems and independent test & evaluation assessments of advanced development capabilities
  - Cognizant test director on multiple laboratory test events and exercises (while serving as an independent test & evaluation engineering analyst evaluating advanced development capabilities planned for insertion on sonar platforms)
  - o Cognizant project manager signing off on multiple engineering reports and analysis studies
- General Dynamics Electric Boat
  - o Lead author on 3 engineering reports regarding technology insertion efforts on US submarines
  - o Lead author on report and catalog of unmanned undersea vehicle technologies
  - o Co-lead on technology exploration effort regarding multidisciplinary design optimization
  - o Cognizant noise control engineer signing off on over 50 engineering drawings and supporting engineer regarding three temporary alterations

#### **PRESENTATIONS**

- **J. Blochberger**, "Analysis of Structural Acoustic Design Variables for a Periodically Stiffened Plate Using the Finite Element Method," ASME 2019 International Mechanical Engineering Congress & Exposition, Salt Lake City, UT, USA, 2019.
- B. Ayliff, **J. Blochberger**, N. Foy, P. Norman, and T. Smith, "Smart Acoustic Monitoring System," NASA Acoustics Technical Working Group, Hampton, VA, USA, 2015.

## **OTHER PROJECTS**

- **J. Blochberger**, "Simulating Schelling's Segregation Model in MATLAB Using An Iterative 2D Convolution Approach," Post-Masters Research Project, 2021. <a href="https://github.com/joeblochberger/ABM-Schelling">https://github.com/joeblochberger/ABM-Schelling</a>
- **J. Blochberger,** "Simulating a Reverberation Effect Using Convolution in MATLAB," Post-Masters Research Project, 2020. <a href="https://github.com/joeblochberger/ConvolutionReverbProject">https://github.com/joeblochberger/ConvolutionReverbProject</a>
- **J. Blochberger**, "Performance of Reactive Acoustic Mufflers," Wolfram Demonstrations Project, 2016. <a href="https://demonstrations.wolfram.com/PerformanceOfReactiveAcousticMufflers/">https://demonstrations.wolfram.com/PerformanceOfReactiveAcousticMufflers/</a>
- B. Ayliff, **J. Blochberger**, N. Foy, P. Norman, and T. Smith, "Smart Acoustic Monitoring System Virginia Tech Senior Mechanical Capstone Project," 2014-2015. Sponsored by the NASA Langley Research Center and the National Institute of Aerospace. Advised by Prof. Christopher Fuller. <a href="https://youtu.be/0nKAHMkX3tY">https://youtu.be/0nKAHMkX3tY</a>

## **HONORS / AWARDS**

- Gordon Croft Endowed Fellowship, The Johns Hopkins University Whiting School of Engineering, 2022
- Special Achievement Award, The Johns Hopkins University Applied Physics Lab, 2020
- Janney Explore Award, The Johns Hopkins University Applied Physics Lab, 2019
- Excellence in Mentoring Award, General Dynamics Electric Boat, 2019
- James Brown Memorial Scholarship, General Dynamics Electric Boat Management Association, 2017
- Best in Innovation & Creativity Award, Virginia Tech Mechanical Engineering Department, 2015
- Dean's List, Virginia Tech, 2014

## **MEMBERSHIPS / AFFILIATIONS**

American Society of Mechanical Engineers (ASME), 2012 to present Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics (SIAM), 2022 to present Acoustical Society of America, 2014 to 2019

## **PROFESSIONAL SERVICE**

- Technical Committee Member
  - o ASME Noise Control & Acoustics Division (NCAD), Structural Acoustics
- Conference Organizer
  - Session Chair, Analytical & Computational Vibrations & Acoustics, 2022 ASME International Mechanical Engineering Congress & Exposition
  - Session Chair (Co-Chair with Dr. Linda Zhu, University of Michigan-Flint), Analytical & Computational Vibrations & Acoustics, 2021 ASME International Mechanical Engineering Congress & Exposition
  - Topic Organizer, Analytical & Computational Vibrations & Acoustics, 2020 ASME International Mechanical Engineering Congress & Exposition
- Conference Paper Reviewer
  - o ASME International Mechanical Engineering Congress & Exposition, 2017-2022